Good morning, everyone in Tateshina, Nagano Prefecture!
Hm? Sensei, why Tateshina?
Well, the corn was delicious the other day.
It's a wonderful place, isn't it?
I'm Hiroto, the English teacher of the Dajo-e-kai, and I'll catch you with my heart.
Hey everyone, this is Akinorosa.
And I'm David Evans.
Well, I like these stories better than his corny jokes.
Oh, God.
Well, let's get started.
Lesson 136
説明ルールその2文修飾
今日のキーセンテンスはこちら
He'll perform with us until the day he dies.
説明ルールの練習を続けましょう。
今回は場所、時の修飾語句など文修飾について学びます。
それでは今日のダイアログから確認しましょう。
デスパレートラッツのバンドマネジャー、ステイシーがビルと話しています。
デレックにケリー・キング賞への出演依頼があったことについてのようですね。
ビル、ディジー・ヒュー・ダッ・デレック・ウォー・イン・ヴァイティッド・トゥ・ケリー・キング・トゥ・トゥ・トゥ・ショー?
Yeah, Derek told me.
Are you okay with that?
Yeah.
Sure. People forget that Derek's one of the original members of the band.
I'm the new guy, really.
But he left the band. You're not mad about that?
That's all behind us. He's back now.
He'll perform with us until the day he dies.
How do you know?
That's the way it goes with old rockers.
Bill, did you hear that Derek was invited to Kelly King's talk show?
Did you hear?
Yeah, Derek told me.
Are you okay with that?
アイオーケイウィッダット これはもう丸ごと覚えてしまって
差し支えのない便利さを持った表現ですね
ウィッ これはそのことと一緒にいてOKですかと言っているわけです
もちろんさ デレックがこのバンドの発足メンバーの一人だということを
みんな忘れているね 実は僕の方が新人なんだ
But he left the band. You're not mad about that?
でも彼はバンドから出て行ったのよ。そのこと怒っていないの?
That's all behind us. He's back now. He'll perform with us until the day he dies.
そんなことはすべて過去のことさ。今彼はまた戻ってきた。
これからは死ぬまで僕たちと一緒に演奏するだろうね。
How do you know?
どうしてわかるの?
さあ、ここのHow、プロセスを尋ねるWH語でしたね。
That's the way it goes with old rockers.
昔かたきのロックンローラーとはそういうものさ。
Grammar and Vocabulary
文法と語彙のポイントを確認します。
まず確認するのはビルのこのセリフ。
People forget that Derek's one of the original members of the band.
人々はデレクがこのバンドの補足メンバーの一人だということを忘れています。
リポート文の形です。
forget 忘れているの内容をざっと説が説明展開していますね。
ここで使われた that に注目しましょう。
that のイメージは導く。
what is that ?
あれは何?と言えば、聞き手の注意を遠くにあるものに導くことができますね。
ざっと説でも働きは変わりません。
forgetと述べてから、何を忘れているのかというと、
とその内容に正確に滑らかに導くために用いられる補助的要素として働いているんです。
さてもう一つ、ビルのセリフを確認しましょう。
That's the way it goes with old rockers.
それが昔のロックンローラーに合うやり方です。
The way, やり方、方法、なりゆきの後ろに説を並べ、その説明としています。
説明ルール、説明は後ろに置くが生み出す形の一つ。
That's the way life goes.
人生とはそうしたものだ。
などよく使われます。
ちなみにgoのイメージは進んでいく。
goは行くという訳語を覚えるだけではなく、
ある場所から離れ進んでいく様子をイメージしてくださいね。
それではもう一度ダイアログを聞いてみましょう。
Bill, did you hear that Derek was invited to Kelly King's talk show?
Yeah, Derek told me.
Are you okay with that?
Sure. People forget that Derek's one of the original members of the band. I'm the new guy, really.
But he left the band. You're not mad about that?
That's all behind us. He's back now. He'll perform with us until the day he dies.
How do you know?
That's the way it goes with old rockers.
Target forms.
会話に役立つ典型表現を身につけましょう。
まずは今日のキーセンテンスを改めて確認します。
He'll perform with us until the day he dies.
彼は亡くなる日まで私たちと演奏するでしょう。
英語では状況が生じた場所、時を述べるフレーズは文末な定位置。
それは説明ルール説明は後ろに置くが働いているからです この文で until the day he dies は he'll perform with us の時を説明するためその後ろに置かれているんです
それでは早速キーセンテンスの練習を始めていきましょう
プラクティス
時や場所を表すフレーズというのは、語順は日本語と反転します。
しっかりと英語の語順で練習するようにしましょう。
まずは、He'll perform with us. どうぞ。
He'll perform with us. どうぞ。
さあ、その後ろに、ポンと時を示すフレーズで説明する気持ちで、
until 以下をつなげていきます。
He'll perform with us until the day he dies.
はい、OKです。
それでは、その他の例も一緒に身につけていきましょう。
We had lunch at the mall.
私たちはショッピングモールでランチしました。
We had lunch on the second floor.
私たちは2階でランチしました。
場所を示すフレーズを説明の意識で後ろに置きます。
I work out in the morning.
私は朝トレーニングをします。
I work out for an hour.
私は1時間トレーニングをします。
時を示すフレーズも文末に、説明を展開する意識でI work outの後ろに置きます。
I can't focus with you looking at me.
あなたが私を見ていたら集中できません。
二重状況のwith、withで同時に起こっている状況を説明します。
with以降はyouとlooking at meを並べるだけで文的な内容を構成しています。
説明ルールが生み出す形です。
私は車の中で空港に向かっているところです。
I'm in the car, or I-N-G-Kを使い、同時に起こっている状況で説明。
ほら、英語は並べるだけで説明できる気軽な言葉なんです。
それでは、今紹介した表現を、
デイビッドさん、ローザさんと一緒に声に出して練習してください。
All right, everyone, it's time for today's practice.
We'll be using the 説明ルール, so please put the explanation at the end.
All right, let's practice.
Repeat after us, everyone.
We had lunch at the mall.
We had lunch on the second floor.
Great work. Let's keep going.
I work out in the morning.
I work out for an hour.
OK, here's the next one.
I can't focus with you looking at me.
OK, one more.
I'm in the car heading to the airport.
I'm in the car, heading to the airport.
Unlock your potential.
Repetition is the key.
Great work!
Grammar in action!
文習食を含む文を作りましょう。
まずはこちら。
ルーク、彼はちょっと前にロビーにいましたよ。
彼のことを見なかったのですか؟
さあ、これをノーヒントでいきます。
ルーク、彼はちょっと前にロビーにいましたよ。
彼のことを見なかったのですか?
私たちのおすすめは?
ルーク、彼はロビーにいましたよ。
彼を見なかったのですか?
Luke, he was in the lobby a minute ago. Did you not see him?
He was in the lobby. No satsumei ga a minute ago. Bunmatsu ga teiichi desu.
Did you not? No kaari ni didn't you? Demo okey desu yo.
Dewa ondoku denshu desu.
Luke, he was in the lobby a minute ago. Did you not see him?
それでは次の問題私たちは子供たちを近くに置いて話すべきではありません別の部屋に行きましょうこれもノーヒントできましょう私たちは子供たちを近くに置いて話すべきではありません別の部屋に行きましょう
We shouldn't talk with the kids nearby. Let's go to another room.
二重教のwith。
with の後ろは the kids イコール nearby 近く という文的な内容。
では音読練習です。
We shouldn't talk with the kids nearby. Let's go to another room.
それではもう一問 お父さんはドライブウェイにいて車を洗っています
彼の週末の儀式なのです 儀式これはリトルと言います
お父さんはドライブウェイにいて車を洗っています 彼の週末の儀式なのです
私たちのおすすめは?
Dad's in the driveway washing the car. It's his weekend ritual.
同時に起こっていることを動詞ING形で気軽に説明。
では音読練習しましょう。
Dad's in the driveway washing the car. It's his weekend ritual.
Hey guys, do you have any rituals?
Oh, for me, Sunday is laundry day and folding the laundry after it's clean, that's my ritual.
It's very precise, it's always the same way and it clears my mind and spirit.
I see. How about you, Rosa?
Well, I have a morning ritual which consists of going out and taking care of the horses.
I see. It's nice to be able to repeat the same thing over and over again.
That's all for today.
Bye!